DANIELA MASSICETI

1 Denison Street Sydney, NSW 2060, Australia Senior Researcher (Machine Learning)
Microsoft Research, Sydney

daniela.massiceti@gmail.com https://danielamassiceti.github.io

SUMMARY

I am an interdisciplinary researcher in machine learning (ML) and human-computer interaction with a passion for building technologies that empower marginalised groups of people. My core interests lie in developing ML models that can power interactive experiences across a range of domains - from accessibility to mixed reality. In particular, my research focusses on Teachable AI systems - systems that can learn on-the-fly from small amounts of noisy, real-world data provided by an end-user. I hold a PhD in Machine Learning/Computer Vision and a MSc in Neuroscience from the University of Oxford, and a BSc in Electrical & Computer Engineering from the University of Cape Town. My full research portfolio can be found here.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Researcher. Microsoft Research, Sydney

Aug 2022-present

- Relocated to Sydney with the Teachable AI Experiences (TaiX) team. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE

Senior Researcher. Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Apr 2021-Jul 2022

- Member of Teachable AI Experiences (TaiX) team. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE
- Machine learning lead in the winning team of the global internal Microsoft Hackathon (Oct~2021)
- Recipient of the Innovating for the Future Award at the Microsoft Ability Summit (May 2022)

Researcher. Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Feb 2020-Mar 2021

- Member of Project Tokyo team. Manager: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE
- Collected the ORBIT dataset and open-sourced the ORBIT Teachable Object Recognition benchmark (Mar 2021)

Postdoctoral Research Fellow. St Edmund's College, University of Cambridge

Apr 2020-Sep 2022

- Non-stipendiary research fellowship

EDUCATION & SELECTED AWARDS

D.Phil Engineering - Machine Learning (awarded with no corrections), University of Oxford

2015-2019

- Thesis: "Computer Vision & Natural Language Processing for People with Vision Impairment"
- Supervisors: Prof. Philip H.S. Torr, Dr Stephen Hicks. Examiners: Prof. Andrew Zisserman, Prof. Kristen Grauman.
- Nominated in Re-Work's 30 Under 30 Rising Stars in AI (Mar 2019)
- Bronze Engineering Award at STEM for Britain (awarded by UK Parliament House of Commons) (Sept 2018)
- Winner of University of Oxford Tri-Innovate Competition (start-up pitch competition) (Apr 2017)

M.Sc Neuroscience (with distinction), University of Oxford

2014-2015

- Research project w Prof. Rafal Bogacz "Modelling Parkinson's Disease tremor with networks of weakly-coupled oscillators"
- Research project w Dr Stephen Hicks "Sonic Vision: 3D visual-to-audio mappings for non-sighted navigation"

B.Sc Engineering - Electrical & Computer (cum laude), University of Cape Town

2010-2014

- With Prof. Fred Nicolls "Occluded body pose estimation and reconstruction of bed-bound patients for hospital monitoring"
- Best final year thesis (Siemens Prize) and finalist in SAIEE National Student Project Competition (2013)
- Top final year B.Sc Engineering gradudate (Engineering Council of South Africa medal; 2013)
- Top 4^{th} , 3^{rd} & 2^{nd} -vear student in Engineering faculty (2013, 2012, 2011)
- Top 4^{th} , 3^{rd} & 2^{nd} -year student in B.Sc Electrical & Computer Engineering (2013, 2012, 2011)
- UCT Engineering Faculty Dean's Merit List ($\geq 75\%$ average) (2010-2013)
- Golden Key International Honours Society (top academic 15% at UCT) (2010–2013)

National Senior Certificate (IEB South Africa), Holy Rosary School, Johannesburg

1996 - 2009

- Within top 50 Year 12 students nationally (top 5% in \geq 6 IEB subjects across South Africa) (2009)
- Deputy Head Girl, Dux Scholar, School Honours (all-round academic, sporting and cultural excellence) (2009)

Selected Publications. See Google Scholar for full list

- 1. Basu, S., Stanley, M., Bronskill, J., Feizi, S., Massiceti, D., 2022. Hard-Meta-Dataset++: Towards Understanding Few-Shot Performance on Difficult Tasks. In 2022 International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR).
- 2. Wang J., Lukasiewicz, T., Massiceti, D., Hu, X., Pavlovic, V., Neophytou, A., 2022. NP-Match: When Neural Processes meet Semi-Supervised Learning. In 2022 International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML).
- 3. Bronskill, J.*, Massiceti, D.*, Patacchiola, M.*, Hofmann, K., Nowozin, S., Turner, R.E., 2021. *Memory Efficient Meta-Learning with Large Images*. In 2021 Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS).
- Massiceti, D., Zintgraf, L., Bronskill, J., Theodorou, L., Harris, M.T., Cutrell, E., Morrison, C., Hofmann, K. and Stumpf, S., 2021. ORBIT: A Real-World Few-Shot Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition. In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV).
- 5. Theodorou, L., Massiceti, D., Zintgraf, L., Stumpf, S., Morrison, C., Cutrell, E., Harris, M. T. and Hofmann, K, 2021. Disability-first Dataset Creation: Lessons from Constructing a Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition with Blind and Low Vision Data Collectors. In 2021 ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS).
- Grayson, M., Thieme, A., Marques, R., Massiceti, D., Cutrell, E., Morrison, C., 2020. A Dynamic AI System for Extending the Capabilities of Blind People. In Extended Abstracts of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA).
- 7. Massiceti, D.*, Dokania, P.K.*, Siddharth, N.* and Torr, P.H.S., 2018. Visual Dialogue without Vision or Dialogue. In 2018 Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) [Critiquing & Correcting Trends in ML Workshop].
- 8. Massiceti, D., Siddharth, N., Dokania, P.K. and Torr, P.H.S., 2018. *FlipDial: A Generative Model for Two-Way Visual Dialogue*. In IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR). [accepted as oral]
- 9. Massiceti, D., Hicks, S.L. and van Rheede, J.J., 2018. Stereosonic Vision: exploring visual-to-auditory sensory substitution mappings in an immersive virtual reality navigation paradigm. PLOS ONE 13(7): e0199389.
- 10. Hou, Q*, Massiceti, D.*, Dokania, P.K., Wei, Y., Cheng, M.M. and Torr, P.H.S., 2017. *Bottom-up top-down cues for weakly-supervised semantic segmentation*. In 2017 International Conference on Energy Minimization Methods in Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (EMMCVPR).
- 11. Massiceti, D., Krull, A., Brachmann, E., Rother, C. and Torr, P.H.S., 2017. *Random forests versus Neural Networks What's best for camera localization?*. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA).

Patents

- On an innovation for extracting difficult few-shot classification tasks (filed Jan 2023, commercially sensitive)
- On an innovation for a metaverse application (filed Jan 2022, commercially sensitive)

Selected Scholarships & Grants

- Pembroke College Senior Common Room (SCR) Senior Scholarship (2018–2019), Facebook AI Research ParlAI Grant (2017–2019), Skye Foundation PhD Scholarship (2015–2019), University of Oxford Engineering Science Departmental PhD Scholarship (2015–2019), Clarendon Fund MSc Scholarship (2014–2015), University of Cape Town Engineering Faculty BSc Scholarship (2011–2013), Klaus-Jurgen Bathe Scholarship (2012–2013), University of Cape Town Engineering Faculty Entrance Scholarship (2010), and Harry Allschwang Grant (2010).

Selected Presentations

- Panel Discussion, Pursuing a Resilient and Sustainable Global Society Microsoft Research 30th Anniversary Panel Series
 on Generations of Inspirational and Impactful Research

 Dec 2021
- Sponsor Talk, Advancing Real-world Few-shot Learning with the ORBIT Dataset WiML workshop, NeurIPS Dec 2021
- Invited Talk, Using Few-shot Learning to Realize Teachable AI Systems Microsoft Research Summit Oct 2021
- Invited Talk, A Real-World Few-Shot Dataset for Teachable Object Recognition VizWiz workshop, CVPR Jun 2021
- Guest Lecture, An Introduction to Dataset Bias Department of Computer Science, University of Cambridge Feb 2020
- Student Talk, A Generative Model for Visual Dialogue OxBridge Women in Computer Science Conference Mar 2018

INTERNSHIP/CONSULTANCY POSITIONS

Machine Learning Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

June-Dec 2019

- Developed machine learning models which learn to recognise objects after only seeing a few examples (few-shot recognition)
- Contact: Dr Cecily Morrison MBE cecilym@microsoft.com

Machine Learning Intern, OxSight Ltd

Nov 2018

- Developed a machine learning model for predicting which images regions are salient for OxSight's smart-spectacles
- Contact: Dr Stephen Hicks stephen.hicks@oxsight.co.uk

Machine Learning Consultant, London Vision Clinic

May-July 2018

- Consulted on machine learning methods for automatic keratoconus prediction from retinal scans
- Contact: Dr Dan Reinstein dzr@londonvisionclinic.com

Visiting Student, Computer Vision Lab Dresden (CVLD), Technische Universität Dresden

Apr 2015

- Compared methods for image-based camera relocalisation using random forests and neural networks
- The project resulted in a paper which was accepted and published in ICRA 2017
- Contact: Prof Carsten Rother carsten.rother@iwr.uni-heidelberg.de

LEADERSHIP

Co-lead of the VizWiz workshop

2022-present

- VizWiz is an annual workshop at CVPR on computer vision research/technologies for the blind/low-vision community
- I launched the ORBIT Few-Shot Object Recognition Challenge in 2022, a new ML competition at the workshop

Co-lead of the *Deep Learning Indaba*

2017-present

- The Indaba is a globally-recognised community for African inclusion in machine learning and artificial intelligence
- I co-organised the Indaba machine learning summer school in 2018 & 2019
- I co-founded & lead the Mentorship Programme, facilitating 300+ mentorship sessions for African students

Committee member of University of Oxford's Women in Computer Science society

2018 - 2019

- I led the Women in Comuter Science society's industry partnerships (e.g. Google, DeepMind, Microsoft)
- I coordinated termly office visits, technical talks, and coding and interview preparation workshops

Committee member of University of Oxford's Women in Engineering society

2016-2019

I coordinated the 1st Women in Engineering Research Symposium in May 2018

President of Middle Common Room (MCR), Pembroke College

2017

- I was elected to represent the Pembroke College graduate body (350 members) in the College's Governing Body Committee
- I also served as Treasurer and Vice President of the MCR (2015-2017). As Treasurer, I managed an annual cash flow of £40,000-£50,000, and acquired £4000+ funding for academic and cultural events

OUTREACH

- I mentored 1 student in the Oxford Engineering, Science and Technology (OxFEST) Mentorship Scheme 2018–2019
- I mentored 4 students in the Pembroke MCR/JCR Mentorship Scheme

2016 - 2018

- I volunteered 100+ hours at local orphanages, HIV/Aids homes and hospitals

2009 - 2013

I tutored a class of high-school students from a rural South African school in Mathematics, Biology and Physics 2013

REFERENCES ON REQUEST